Guide to the Kevin H. Prendergast papers,
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Kevin H. Prendergast Papers,
1954-1990
Prendergast, Kevin H.
20 lin. ft. (ca. 5,000 items in 48 boxes).
Columbia University. Rare Book and Manuscript Library, New York, NY. 10027
5490814
Biographical Note
Prendergast received his Ph.D. at Columbia in 1954 and then went to the University of Chicago, returning to Columbia as a professor in 1962. He chaired the Columbia astronomy department from 1978 to 1984, retiring in 2000 with a long trail of successful young theorists in his wake. Prendergast was an icon in the field of dynamics of many-body systems. He also was well known for a series of papers in the 1960s and 1970s, written with Geoffrey and Margaret Burbidge, on understanding the rotation curves of galaxies. Numerous theoretical studies of the structure of galaxies followed, and he was a pioneer in the study of X-ray binary systems. In addition to Prendergast's professional accomplishments, he was also a skilled pianist and an avid sailor. During his long career, Prendergast became famous for using yellow legal pads, on which he had scrawled analyses of many problems in astronomical dynamics. His classes were renowned for the exactitude of his standards and the high percentage of faculty in attendance. During one year, regularly attending faculty outnumbered students.
Scope and Content
Correspondence, manuscripts, lectures, notes, and printed materials of Kevin H. Prendergast, a prominent astronomer who worked in the fields off dynamics of many-body systems, the rotation curves of galaxies, and X-ray binary systems.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into 12 series:
Series I: Personal
Series II: Astronomy
Series III: Dynamical Systems and Applied Mathematics
Series IV: Numerical Hydrodynamics
Series V: Applications of Hydrodynamics and Rarified Gas Dynamics
Series VI: Miscellaneous
Series VII: Published Papers
Series VIII: Lecture Notes
Series IX: Astronomy Department/Professional Organizations
Series X: Ephemera
Series XI: Papers by Others
Series XII: Printed Material
Subjects
Columbia University.--Dept. of Astronomy.; Cosmology.; X-ray binaries.; Barred galaxies--Rotation.; Galactic dynamics.; Stellar dynamics.; Spiral galaxies--Rotation.; Dwarf galaxies.; Stars--Clusters.; X-ray sources, Galactic--Accretion.; Asteroids.
Access Restrictions
This collection has no restrictions.
This collection is located off-site. You will need to request this material from the Rare Book and Manuscript Library at least twenty-four (24) hours in advance to use the collection in the Rare Book and Manuscript Library reading room.
Acquisition
Jane Prendergast. Gift, 2/1/2005 2004-2005-M35.
- Series I: Personal
  - Subseries I.1: Photography
    - Photograph (1) (Box 1)
  - Subseries 1.2: Correspondence
    - Chandra (Box 1)
    - Contopolous (Box 1)
    - Penthame (Box 1)
    - Pesch, Peter (Box 1)
    - Slyz, Adrianne (Box 1)
    - Spiegel, Edward (Box 1)
    - Xu, Kun (Box 2)
- Series II: Astronomy
  - Subseries II.1: Cosmology
    - Equations about cosmology, (166 pages ) (Box 3)
  - Subseries II.2: Dynamics of Galaxies: General
    - Galactic Dynamics (Box 3)
    - Gravitational slab problem (Box 3)
    - One-dimensional self-gravitating gas (Box 3)
    - Time dependent one-dimensional stellar system (Box 3)
    - Self consistent galaxy models (axisymmetric) (Box 3)
    - Instability of rings (of mass) (Box 4)
    - Computer simulation of galactic evolution (Box 4)
    - Stochastic star formation in disk galaxies (mathematical description of a game theory) (Box 4)
    - Stellar dynamics with star formation (Box 4)
    - “Oseen” approximation based on streamlines, etc. (Box 4)
    - Theoretical studies of M101 (Box 4)
  - Subseries II.3: Dynamics of Galaxies: Spiral Galaxies
    - Linear spiral structure (Box 5)
    - Stability of spiral arm shocks (Box 5)
    - Thin gas disk: asymptotic theory of spiral arms (warped disk as finite system of coupled rings) (Box 5)
    - Spiral Arm Problems: Linblad Resonance (Box 5)
  - Subseries II.4: Dynamics of Galaxies: Barred Spiral Galaxies
    - Barred Spirals, [1974?] (Box 5)
    - Barred Spirals (Box 5)
    - Barred spiral galaxies (I, II, III, IV, V, VI, VII, VIII), (1960s, 1970s) (Box 6)
    - Barred spiral galaxies—some plots & shock waves in barred spiral galaxies (Box 6)
    - Barred spirals Roche modes (Box 6)
    - Gradient wind approximation (Box 6)
    - Potential of oblate spheroid (Box 6)
    - Symmetry properties (Box 6)
    - Theoretical studies of gas flow in barred spiral galaxies (Box 7)
    - Barred spiral shocks (Box 7)
    - Barred spiral galaxies: material for a talk based on a paper on “Theoretical studies of gas flows in barred spiral galaxies” by K. Prendergast (Box 7)
    - Barred spiral galaxies [talk], Yale, 1978 (Box 7)
    - Talk given by Kevin Prendergast on barred spiral galaxies, 1982 (Box 7)
  - Subseries II.5: Dynamics of Galaxies: Dwarf Elliptical Galaxies (and Elliptical Galaxies)
    - Dwarf elliptical galaxies--analytical approximation (two-fluid with gravity) (Box 7)
    - Two-fluid spherical models (Box 8)
    - Analytic approximation, two-fluid with gravity (Box 8)
    - Modeling the formation of elliptical and dwarf galaxies using a spheroidal two-fluid system with self-gravity (Box 8)
    - Numerical Simulations of the Formation of Dwarf Ellipticals (I,II, III, IV, V) (Box 8)
    - Marseille collaboration papers (published) (Box 8)
    - Marseille (Box 9)
    - Marseille (Box 10)
    - Marseille (Box 11)
    - Marseille (Box 12)
    - Marseille (Box 13)
    - Marseille numerical simulation results and some theoretical analysis of those models (Box 14)
    - Marseille numerical simulations (Box 15)
    - Marseille numerical simulations (Box 16)
    - Marseille numerical simulations (Box 17)
    - Marseille numerical simulation results performed at Marseille Observatory, France (collaborators Lia Athanassoula et al.), 1988 (Box 18)
    - Numerical models (including programs) and results for one-dimensional two-fluid (Cartesian grid) and Marseille models (Box 18)
    - Dwarf galaxies formation models (Marseille 1994) and other numerical modeling results (including programs) (Box 18)
    - Various numerical simulation results of the Marseille collaboration [mostly in the form of diagrams] (Box 19)
    - Marseille Observatory simulation results used for Columbia Astrofest talk, 1996 (Box 19)
    - Dwarf elliptical galaxy formation, talk given at Columbia, 1990 (Box 19)
  - Subseries II.6: Dynamics of Galaxies: Star-Gas Interactions in Galaxies
    - Two-fluid (stars and gas) linear stability analysis, 1980 (Box 19)
    - Two-fluid hydrodynamic model, 1978 (Box 19)
    - 3-fluid model (gas, high mass star, low mass star) (Box 19)
    - Two-fluid star-gas model [talk], Charlottesville, Virginia (Box 20)
    - Talk given at European Southern Observatory, Munich, Germany (Box 19)
  - Subseries II.7: Star Clusters
    - Escape of stars from clusters: statistical mechanical approach, 1980s (Box 20)
  - Subseries II.8: Accretion Disks
    - X-ray generation in accretion disk in binary systems, gas streams in close binary systems (Box 20)
    - Binary Stellar Systems (Box 20)
  - Subseries II.9: Asteroid
    - Asteroid, 1950s (Box 21)
    - Rotating asteroid, 1950s (Box 21)
    - Rotating asteroid (I, II, III, IV, V), 1950 (Box 21)
  - Subseries II.10: Few- and N-body Problems, and Celestial Mechanics
    - Statistics of the gravitational three- and four-body problems (Box 22)
    - Statistics of three-body problem (Box 22)
    - N-body problem, 1970 (Box 23)
    - Large N problems (N-particle systems) (Box 23)
    - N-Body, NYU, 1980 (Box 23)
    - Celestial mechanics I (Box 23)
    - Celestial mechanics II (Box 23)
  - Subseries II.11: Hydrodynamics, Astrophysical Fluid Dynamics, and Gas-Kinetic Theory
    - A series of analytic studies (notebooks I-VI) on hydrodynamics, as moment equations of the Boltzmann equation (Box 24)
    - Singularities of one dimensional hydrodynamic system using pseudo Liouville equation (Box 24)
    - Gravity in the BGK scheme for hydrodynamics (Box 24)
    - Solution of the Krook equation at shock (Box 24)
    - Collisional hydrodynamic scheme (CHS)—theoretical derivation of the method (Box 24)
    - Radial flow (Box 25)
    - Wave-driven winds—several manuscripts (Box 25)
    - Breaking waves, 1984 (Box 25)
    - Nonlinear convection, [1980s?] (Box 25)
    - Nonlinear convection—rational approximation, [1981?] (Box 25)
    - Turbulence sphere, 1970s (Box 25)
    - Angular momentum (of turbulent fluid) (Box 26)
    - Hydrodynamics—variational principle (Box 26)
    - Burger’s equation (Box 26)
    - Burger’s equation—singularities (inviscid) (Box 26)
    - Burger’s equation—two-dimensional inviscid (Box 26)
    - Burger’s equation with viscosity and potential (Box 27)
    - Burger’s equation (two-dimensional inviscid)—singularities (talk given at Columbia) (Box 27)
    - Gas Kinetic Theory in General (including Radiative Transfer) (Box 27)
    - Hydrodynamics in General (Box 27)
  - Subseries II.12: Magnetohydrodynamics
    - Hydromagnetic similarity solutions I, 1975 (Box 27)
    - Hydromagnetic similarity solutions II (Box 27)
    - Axisymmetric time-dependent self-similar force-free fields (Box 27)
    - Force-free fields (axisymmetric) (Box 27)
- Series III: Dynamical Systems and Applied Mathematics
  - Hamiltonian system (H=1⁄2(X.2+Y.2+X2+Y2)+X2Y) (Box 28)
  - Variational principle for Hamiltonian systems and vanishing Henyey determinant, [1980s?] (Box 28)
  - Duffing equation (Box 28)
  - Duffing with driving (Box 29)
  - Duffing equation: NR correction (Box 29)
  - Duffing, van der Pol—high order approximation (rational approximation, [1980s?] (Box 29)
  - Van der Pol oscillator, [1980s?] (Box 29)
  - Van der Pol oscillator (Box 29)
  - Hamilton-Jacobi equation (Box 29)
  - Fourier-Pade (x..+x7=0), higher order correction (Box 29)
  - Fourier-Pade equation (Box 29)
  - Fourier Pade equation ( (x..+x3=0), higher order correction (Box 29)
  - Fourier-Pade integration (Box 30)
  - Pade: 2D: ordinary differential equations of higher order, 1D: quadratic, etc. (Box 30)
  - Mathieu equation (Box 30)
  - Mathieu equation: two-point approximation (Box 30)
  - kdV equation with implicit function (Box 30)
  - Liouville equation (Box 30)
  - Liouville equation (Woods Hole), 1969 (Box 30)
  - Eckonal equation (Box 30)
  - Rational approximation near w=0 (potential maximum) (Box 30)
  - Rational-function orbits (Box 30)
  - Rational approximation for a Hamiltonian system (Box 31)
  - Rational approximation for non-linear ordinary differential equations (Box 31)
  - “N/D”—rational approximation (Box 31)
  - Discussion on the paper “Rational Approximations for a Hamiltonian System” (Box 31)
  - Non-linear approximation: general discussions (Box 31)
  - Non-linear approximation for ordinary differential equation (Box 31)
  - Non-linear approximation for periodic orbits in a Hamiltonian System (Box 31)
  - Non-linear oscillations (Box 32)
  - Non-linear dynamics (Box 32)
  - Singular point approximation—solution of D.E. at an assumed pole, [1980s?] (Box 32)
  - Singularities and bifurcation (Box 32)
  - (Equation) periodic solutions (Box 32)
  - Bifurcation and vanishing of Henyey matrix and other difference equations (Box 32)
  - “Implicit” form of solutions to ordinary difference equations (Box 32)
  - Difference equations with noise (Box 32)
  - Stretched coordinate systems (Box 32)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 32)
  - Talk on Non-linear mechanics (Fourier-Pade), New York University (Box 32)
- Series IV: Numerical Hydrodynamics
  - Numerical hydrodynamics: beam schemes (Box 33)
  - Beam scheme (Box 33)
  - Continuous beam scheme (Box 33)
  - Three-dimensional axisymmetric cylindrical beam scheme with body force (Box 33)
  - Numerical Hydrodyamics from gas-kinetic theory (Box 34)
  - Numerical Navier-Stokes solution from gas-kinetic theory-K Xu, and K Prendergast (Box 34)
  - Numerical Navier-Stokes solution from gas-kinetic theory—Kun Xu and Kevin Prendergast (Box 34)
  - Paper II: final copy (Box 34)
  - Paper II: KX and KHP Navier-Stokes Paper (Box 34)
  - Applied Math Seminar Notes (non-linear equations) (Box 34)
  - Numerical Hydro-Spare (Box 35)
  - Miscellaneous notes on non-linear dynamics and hydrodynamics Codes (Box 35)
  - Difference scheme from Hamiltonian principle (Box 35)
  - Talk given at Supercomputer Conference, Santa Clara, 1989 (Box 35)
  - Numerical hydrodynamics—talks at, Woods Hole & Columbia University, 7/25/2000 & 9/27/2000 (Box 35)
  - Applied Math Seminar Notes (non-linear equations) (Box 35)
- Series V: Applications of Hydrodynamics and Rarified Gas Dynamics
  - Slider bearing (for IBM Research), 1980s (Box 35)
  - Long mean-free-path approximation for slider bearing, 1980s (Box 35)
  - Viscous flow with surface tension (for IBM Research, [1980s?] (Box 36)
  - Water waves (test cases) (for IBM Research), 1980 (Box 36)
- Series VI: Miscellaneous
  - Optics (and singularities)—Catastrophe Optics?, 1980 (Box 36)
  - Spectral Line Formation (Box 36)
  - Photoelectrical Photometry (Box 36)
  - Thomas-Fermi quantization (Box 36)
  - Computation of curves of constant P (a,b,c) (Box 36)
  - Statistics (Box 36)
  - Research Proposals: National Science Foundation (Box 36)
- Series VII: Published Papers
  - KHP Bibliography (Box 37)
  - Reprints of K Prendergast (Box 37)
  - Marseille Collaboration Papers (Box 37)
  - Prendergast, Kevin On the color-magnitude diagram of the globular cluster Centauri, 1954, (Ph.D. thesis ) (Box 37)
  - Some published papers related to two-fluid model for stars and gas in galaxies (Box 38)
  - Nature of some X-Ray sources, 1968 (Box 38)
  - Some published papers of galactic dynamics (Box 38)
  - Preprints of various published papers by K. Prendergast (Box 38)
  - University of Paris symposium on numerical simulation of formation and evolution of elliptical galaxies (Box 38)
  - Tsiang, Eugene Yu-Kong The accretion disk model of X-ray stars, Columbia University, 1977, (Ph.D. thesis ) (Box 38)
  - Numerical hydrodynamic solutions based on BGK (Box 38)
  - Xu, Kun Numerical hydrodynamics from gas-kinetic theory, Columbia University, [n.d.], (Ph.D. thesis ) (Box 39)
  - Gravitational potential of a disk spiral galaxy—B. Barbanis and K. Prendergast (Box 39)
  - Time-Independent Gravitational Fields in the BGK Scheme for Hydrodynamics (Slyz, Prendergast) (Box 39)
- Series VIII: Lecture Notes
  - Subseries VIII.1: Graduate School Courses (developed by K. Prendergast)
    - Mechanics (Vol I, II) (Box 39)
    - Classical mechanics (Box 39)
    - Basic astronomical data (Box 39)
    - Contemporary Astrophysics (Box 40)
    - Astrophysics (Box 40)
    - Astrophysics II (Box 40)
    - Special relativity (Box 40)
    - Relativity, gravitation, and black holes (Box 40)
    - Radiation transfer (Box 40)
    - Gas stream in close binary systems (Box 40)
    - Galactic dynamics (Box 40)
    - Galactic accretion (Box 40)
    - Introduction to Stellar Evolution (Box 41)
    - Electromagnetic theory (Box 41)
    - Statistical Mechanics and Thermodynamics (Box 41)
    - Statistical Mechanics (Box 41)
    - Prendergast Lectures for Correction, Jan 10, 1969 (Box 41)
    - Statistical Mechanics (Box 41)
    - Continuum Physics, Fall 78 (Box 41)
    - Hydro Course notes (Box 41)
    - Classical Theory of Radiation I (Box 41)
    - Classical Theory of Radiation II (Box 41)
  - Subseries VIII.2: Lecture notes on undergraduate courses
    - Special relativity (Box 41)
  - Subseries VIII.3: Lecture notes on graduate school courses (developed by others)
    - Galactic dynamics (by L. Woltijer) (Box 41)
    - Quantum Mechanics (Box 42)
    - Electromagnetic theory (Box 42)
    - Classical mechanics (Box 42)
    - GNRI—Generalized Newton-Raphson code for boundary value problem developed by Norman Baker (Box 42)
- Series IX: Astronomy Department/Professional Organizations
  - Astronomy Department/Professional Organizations material (Box 43)
- Series X: Ephemera
  - Diskettes (Box 44)
  - Glass Plates (Box 44)
  - Reel (Box 44)
- Series XI: Papers by Others
  - Paters by others (Box 45 & 46)
- Series XII: Printed Material
  - Printed Material (Box 47-48)